<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on   Christos Pitsikas</title>
    <link>https://christospitsi.github.io/tags/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on   Christos Pitsikas</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2017 Christos Pitsikas</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:09:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christospitsi.github.io/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Logistic Regression 1</title>
      <link>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/logistic-regression-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:09:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/logistic-regression-1/</guid>
      <description>For the purposes of this post we will use the Weekly dataset, included in the ISLR library. The dataset consists of percentage returns for the S&amp;amp;P 500 stock index between 1990 and 2010.
In the data frame, there are 1089 observations and the following variables:
In the data frame, there are 1089 observations and the following 9 variables:
 year: Year that the observation was recorded lag1: Percentage return for previous week lag2: Percentage return for 2 weeks previous lag3: Percentage return for 3 weeks previous lag4: Percentage return for 4 weeks previous lag5: Percentage return for 5 weeks previous volume: Volume of shares traded (average number of daily shares traded in billions) today: Percentage return for this week direction: A factor with levels Down and Up indicating whether the market had a positive or negative return on a given week  Below we can see a numerical summary for all predictors:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linear Regression 1</title>
      <link>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/linear-regression-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2017 22:52:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/linear-regression-1/</guid>
      <description>In this exercise we create some simulated data and fit a simple linear regression model. The simulated data are generated using the rnorm() function with mean 0 and variance 1. The generated data are stored in vector X.
set.seed(1) x &amp;lt;- rnorm(100, 0, 1)  In addition to the data, we generate vector eps which will represent the error of the model.
eps &amp;lt;- rnorm(100, 0, sqrt(0.25))  We create vector y based on the below linear equation in which β0 = -1 and β1 = 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Simple R Commands - Boston Dataset</title>
      <link>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/some-simple-r-commands---boston-dataset/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2017 21:06:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/some-simple-r-commands---boston-dataset/</guid>
      <description>The Boston data set, part of the MASS library, contains information regarding the housing values in the suburbs of Boston.
The dimensions of the data frame are shown below:
library (MASS) dim(Boston) ## [1] 506 14  The 506 rows of the dataset correspond to 506 observations, each of which has 14 predictors (number of columns).
Using pairs() function, we generate scatterplots for all combinations between predictors in order to try to figure out any possible associations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistics 101</title>
      <link>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/statistics-101/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2017 19:52:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/statistics-101/</guid>
      <description>Mean, Median and Mode A few introductory words about the very basic definitions and R commands of measures of central tendency and spread in statistics.
Suppose we ask a group of 10 students how many brothers and sisters they have and the number obtained are as follows:
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; (2&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;3&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;0&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;5&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;2&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;1 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;1&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;0&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;3 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;3)
The mean of our data is the arithmetic average of the observations whereas the median is the middle value when the observations are ranked in order.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>