<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on   Christos Pitsikas</title>
    <link>https://christospitsi.github.io/tags/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on   Christos Pitsikas</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2017 Christos Pitsikas, Powered by Hugo and Cocoa-Eh theme</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2017 10:06:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christospitsi.github.io/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Cross validation on a simulated dataset</title>
      <link>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/cross-validation-on-a-simulated-dataset/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2017 10:06:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/cross-validation-on-a-simulated-dataset/</guid>
      <description>For the purposes of this exercise, we generate the simulated data using the below equation:
set.seed(1) x &amp;lt;- rnorm(100) y &amp;lt;- x -2*x^2 + rnorm(100)  Our data set consists of 100 values for x (n = 100) and one predictor (p = 1) The function for the calculation of y is of the below form:
Y = β0 + β1X + β2X2 + ϵ. In our example, β0 = 0, β1 = 1, β2 = −2 and the error is a randomly generated number.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>S&amp;P 500 stock exchange - A &#39;for loop&#39; Leave-one-out cross validation solution</title>
      <link>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/sp-500-stock-exchange---a-for-loop-leave-one-out-cross-validation-solution/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 23:24:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/sp-500-stock-exchange---a-for-loop-leave-one-out-cross-validation-solution/</guid>
      <description>The Leave-one-out cross validation test error can be estimated using the R build-in function cv.glm, however, it is worth exploring an alternative solution, using functions glm, predict.glm and a for loop. For the purposes of this exercise, we will revisit the percentage returns for the S&amp;amp;P 500 stock index included in Weekly dataset.
We first fit a logistic regression model which predicts Direction using Lag1 and Lag2 variables and the whole dataset as training set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The credit card problem - Validation set approach</title>
      <link>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/the-credit-card-problem---validation-set-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 22:17:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/the-credit-card-problem---validation-set-approach/</guid>
      <description>Default is a simulated data set from ISLR library with information on ten thousand customers. We are interested in predicting whether a customer will default using the following predictors:
 balance: The average balance that the customer has remaining on their credit card after making their monthly payment income: Income of the customer.  We fit a logistic regression model which uses income and balance to predict default and then we print a summary with all the calculated values.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting vehicle gas consumption</title>
      <link>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/predicting-vehicle-gas-consumption/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2017 21:48:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/predicting-vehicle-gas-consumption/</guid>
      <description>The Auto data set, included in the ISLR library provides us with details for 392 vehicles and the following variables for each observation:
 Mpg: Miles per gallon cylinders: Number of cylinders (4-8) displacement: Engine displacement (cu. inches) horsepower: Engine power weight: Vehicle weight (lbs.) acceleration: Time to accelerate from 0 to 60 mph (sec.) year: Model Year (modulo 100) origin: Origin of the car (1. American, 2. European, 3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>S&amp;P 500 stock exchange - Logistic regression model</title>
      <link>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/sp-500-stock-exchange---logistic-regression-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:09:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/sp-500-stock-exchange---logistic-regression-model/</guid>
      <description>For the purposes of this post we will use the Weekly dataset, included in the ISLR library. The dataset consists of percentage returns for the S&amp;amp;P 500 stock index between 1990 and 2010.
In the data frame, there are 1089 observations and the following variables:
 year: Year that the observation was recorded lag1: Percentage return for previous week lag2: Percentage return for 2 weeks previous lag3: Percentage return for 3 weeks previous lag4: Percentage return for 4 weeks previous lag5: Percentage return for 5 weeks previous volume: Volume of shares traded (average number of daily shares traded in billions) today: Percentage return for this week direction: A factor with levels Down and Up indicating whether the market had a positive or negative return on a given week  Below we can see a numerical summary for all predictors:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A simple linear regression model using simulated data</title>
      <link>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/a-simple-linear-regression-model-using-simulated-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2017 22:52:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/a-simple-linear-regression-model-using-simulated-data/</guid>
      <description>In this exercise we create some simulated data and fit a simple linear regression model. The simulated data are generated using the rnorm() function with mean 0 and variance 1. The generated data are stored in vector X.
set.seed(1) x &amp;lt;- rnorm(100, 0, 1)  In addition to the data, we generate vector eps which will represent the error of the model.
eps &amp;lt;- rnorm(100, 0, sqrt(0.25))  We create vector y based on the below linear equation in which β0 = -1 and β1 = 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few &#39;Hello World&#39; R commands and Boston housing prices</title>
      <link>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/a-few-hello-world-r-commands-and-boston-housing-prices/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2017 21:06:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/a-few-hello-world-r-commands-and-boston-housing-prices/</guid>
      <description>The Boston data set, part of the MASS library, contains information regarding the housing values in the suburbs of Boston.
The dimensions of the data frame are shown below:
library (MASS) dim(Boston) ## [1] 506 14  The 506 rows of the dataset correspond to 506 observations, each of which has 14 predictors (number of columns).
Using pairs() function, we generate scatterplots for all combinations between predictors in order to try to figure out any possible associations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistics 101</title>
      <link>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/statistics-101/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2017 19:52:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christospitsi.github.io/blog/statistics-101/</guid>
      <description>Mean, Median and Mode A few introductory words about the very basic definitions and R commands of measures of central tendency and spread in statistics.
Suppose we ask a group of 10 students how many brothers and sisters they have and the number obtained are as follows:
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; (2&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;3&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;0&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;5&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;2&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;1 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;1&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;0&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;3 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;3)
The mean of our data is the arithmetic average of the observations whereas the median is the middle value when the observations are ranked in order.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>